Guide to the Larkin family photograph collection, circa 1870s-1920s
George Mason University Libraries
Special Collections Research Center, George Mason University
Larkin family photograph collection
circa 1870s-1920s
George Mason University. Special Collections Research Center.
Larkin family
C0126
0.5 linear ft. (2 boxes)
This collection contains dozens of family photographs from the late-nineteenth and early-twentieth century, exhibiting a range of early photographic technology including albumen prints, tintypes and cyanotypes, as well as gelatin silver prints.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Collection donor unknown.
Historical Information
In the late 19th and early 20th centuries, photography was moving beyond experts and studios and becoming more widespread among non-specialists. Describing Kodak's invetion of Eastman gelatin film in 1886, Mary Lynn Ritzenthaler and Diane Vogt-O'Connor say, "This process, in combination with the dry gelatin emulsion and Kodak's complete developing and printing service, encouraged amateur photography to boom" (45). Earlier popular photographic varieties such as tintypes (images on laquered iron common in the United States in the mid-to-late 1800s) and albumen prints (created using an egg-white emulsion common in the later 1800s) were gradualy overtaken by gelatin silver prints as the main photographic medium in use by professionals and amateurs alike (Ritzenthaler and Vogt-O'Connor, 33-48). As the Victoria and Albert Museum's page on photographic processes notes, gelatin-silver prints "by 1895 had generally replaced albumen prints because they were more stable, did not turn yellow, and were simpler to produce" ('Photographic Processes'). The cyanotype, created using the same process used to make blueprints, never quite achieved the popularity of any of these processes (see Ritzenthaler and Vogt-O'Connor, 33-34).
Scope and Content
This collection contains dozens of family photographs from the late-nineteenth and early-twentieth centuries, exhibiting a range of early photographic technology including albumen prints, tintypes and cyanotypes, as well as gelatin silver prints. A few of the photographs have been hand-tinted. Several photos contain inscriptions of photo studios--including G. W. Davis and Unique--with addresses indicating that many of them were taken in Washington, D.C., Northern Virginia, or Richmond, VA. The photographs range from professional studio portraits to informal group pictures, which appear to have been taken in more rural locales. Several of the photos show Victorian interiors and exteriors as well as horse carriages, row-boats and railroad tracks. Few of the subjects are identified, but photo-envelopes with the collection include the names Ceyton R. Larkin, Charles Rozier Larkin, Paul S. Williams, and Mrs. J. L. Johnson.
Arrangement
Organized largely by photograph type.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Special Collections Research Center also holds the.
Bibliography
Ritzenthaler, Mary Lynn, and Diane O'Connor, with Helena Zinkham et al. "Photographs: Archival Care and Management." Chicago: Society of American Archivists, 2006.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Domestic life. Washington (D.C.)
Document Types:
Albumen prints.; Cyanotypes.; Portraits.; Tintypes.
Contents List
  - Photograph envelopes and receipts from developers, circa early 1900s (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Mounted gelatin silver print of man and boy, circa early 1900s (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Mounted gelatin silver print of man with horse and carriage, circa early 1900s (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Mounted gelatin silver print of child with bicycle, circa early 1900s (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Mounted gelatin silver print of child, circa early 1900s (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Mounted gelatin silver print of woman and two children, circa early 1900s (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Mounted gelatin silver print of women in a field, circa early 1900s (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Mounted gelatin silver print of a child, circa early 1900s (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Mounted silver gelatin print of child on a horse, circa early 1900s (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Tintype of three men, circa 1870s-1880s (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Tintype of a boy and a baby, circa 1870s-1880s (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Tintype of a man and woman, circa 1870s-1880s (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Tintype of a man in glasses, circa 1870s-1880s (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Two gelatin silver prints of a toddler, circa early 1900s (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Two gelatin silver prints of children, circa early 1900s (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Two gelatin silver prints of a girl and toddler, circa early 1900s (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Gelatin silver print of a girl at a piano, circa early 1900s (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Three gelatin silver prints - a man on a horse and young men on a stoop, circa early 1900s (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Gelatin silver print of a man, woman, and girl, circa early 1900s (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Gelatin silver prints of a young man, circa early 1900s (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Gelatin silver print of a man in a hat, circa early 1900s (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Gelatin silver print photographs of a woman, circa 1910s-1920s (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Gelatin silver prints - a woman and an outdoor structure, circa 1910s-1920s (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Mounted prints of a young boy, possibly albumen, circa late 1800s-early 1900s (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Two silver gelatin prints of three men on a stoop, early 1900s (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Silver gelatin print of a man with a lawn mower, circa 1910-1920s (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Albumen print of three children and article on King George of Greece's jubilee, circa 1888 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Silver gelatin print of a man and woman, circa 1910s-1920s (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Albumen carte-de-visite of three children, circa 1888 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Mounted gelatin print of a group of people, circa 1890s-early 1900s (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Tintype of a young man in a frame, circa 1970s-1980s (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Gelatin silver print of three women, man and a child, circa 1910s-1920s (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Gelatin silver print of two women, circa 1910s-1920s (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Gelatin silver print a man and a young child, circa 1910s (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Gelatin silver prints of women with boats, circa early 1900s-1910s (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Albumen prints of infants, circa 1870s-1890s (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Three mounted albumen prints of a boy and girl, circa 1870s-1890s (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Two gelatin silver prints of a house, circa early 1900s (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Gelatin silver print of a man with a horse and carriage, circa early 1900s (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Gelatin silver print of a man riding a horse, circa 1910s-1920s (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Gelatin silver print of a man sitting, circa 1910s-1920s (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Gelatin silver prints of a woman and child, circa 1910s-1920s (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Gelatin silver print of a man and woman laughing, circa 1910s-1920s (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Gelatin silver prints of a house, circa 1910s-1920s (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Gelatin silver print of a woman, circa 1910s-1920s (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Gelatin silver print of a home after snowfall, circa early 1900s (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Gelatin silver print of a dining room, circa early 1900s (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Gelatin silver print of a river, possibly Great Falls of the Potomac, circa early 1900s (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Gelatin silver print of four young women, circa 1910s-1920s (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Gelatin silver print of a man in a suit, circa 1910s-1920s (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Gelatin silver print of railroad tracks, circa early 1900s (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Gelatin silver print of a child, circa early 1900s (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Gelatin silver prints of women and an infant, circa early 1900s (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Three gelatin silver prints of a man, circa early 1900s (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Two gelatin silver prints of three men, circa early 1900s (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Gelatin silver prints of a dock with boats, circa early 1900s (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Cyanotypes of outdoor scenes, circa late 1800s-early 1900s (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Cyanotypes of a man and woman, circa late 1800s-early 1900s (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Cyanotypes of men, women, and children, circa late 1800s-early 1900s (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Cyanotypes of women and children, circa late 1800s-early 1900s (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Cyanotypes of men and a woman, circa late 1800s-early 1900s (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Gelatin silver prints of buildings and a river in the snow, circa 1910s-1920s (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Gelatin silver prints of a man in a suit, circa 1910s-1920s (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Carte de visite of a young man in a uniform, circa 1870s-1890s (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Carte de visite of a young man in a uniform, circa 1870s-1890s (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Gelatin silver prints of a woman and an infant, circa early 1900s (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Gelatin silver prints of children and a woman in a wheelchair, circa 1910s-1920s (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Gelatin silver portrait of a young girl, circa 1910s-1920s (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Gelatin silver print of a man in a suit, circa 1910s-1920s (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Mounted gelatin silver print of three women, circa 1910s-1920s (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Gelatin silver print of a group of people outside, circa early 1900s-1910s (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Report card, class photograph, and family photograph (mounted), 1900s (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Mounted gelatin silver print of a child outdoors, circa early 1900s (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Mounted gelatin silver print of a child on a horse, circa early 1900s (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Mounted gelatin silver prints of a young child outdoors, circa early 1900s (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Mounted print of an infant, circa early 1900s (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Mounted prints of an infant, circa early 1900s (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Gelatin silver and albumen prints of men, women, and children, circa 1880s-early 1900s (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Albumen print of Francis Norville Larkin, photographic postcards, gelatin silver prints, hand-tinted gelatin silver prints, envelopes from photographic developers in Manassas and Charlottesville, VA, circa 1880s-1918 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Cartes de visite of various Larkin family members and others, other mounted photographs, circa 1870s-1890s (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Cartes de visite, possibly a photogravure, circa 1870s-1890s (Box 2, Folder 10)